

Francisco Pablo Flores Taipe

Nationality: Ecuadorian (+49) 17624861016 **Date of birth:** 27/05/1987

Email address: franciscopabloflores@gmail.com

Website: https://www.uni-kassel.de/forschung/en/27/incher/people/flores-francisco

Website: https://www.poverty-action.org/people/francisco-flores

▼ Twitter: https://twitter.com/FrancoPF

• Address: Mönchebergstraße 17, Kassel, 34109 Kassel (Germany)

ABOUT ME

I am a Doctoral student at the University of Kassel (Germany). My research interests are development, inequality, education, behavioral, and gender economics.

I received my MSc. in Economic Behavior and Governance from the University of Kassel in 2018. Between 2018 and 2019, I was also a research fellow at the International Center for Higher Education Research (INCHER).

EDUCATION AND TRAINING

Doctoral candidate in Economics

[14/05/2018 – Current]

Master of Science in Economic Behavior and Governance

University of Kassel [04/2016 – 04/2018]

Address: Kassel (Germany)

Thesis: Showing Life Opportunities: Increasing opportunity-driven entrepreneurship and STEM careers through

online courses in schools. (Supervisor: Dr. Igor Asanov)

Bachelor of Science in Economics

Pontificia Universidad Católica del Ecuador (PUCE) [10/2005 – 12/2011]

Address: Quito (Ecuador)

Thesis: El sector eléctrico ecuatoriano en los últimos 20 años : estrategias para alcanzar la seguridad energética

(Supervisor: MSc. Rubén Flores)

WORK EXPERIENCE

Researcher and lecturer at the Faculty of Economics (FB-07)

University of Kassel [14/05/2018 - Current]

City: Kassel

Country: Germany

Research fields: economics of education, development economics, gender economics, behavioral economics, experimental economics.

Teach courses on:

- Behavioral Economics of Poverty
- Economics of Entrepreneurship
- (Quasi-) Experiments in Entrepreneurship Research
- Field Experiments (Tutorial)
- Intellectual Property Rights (Tutorial)

Short-term Consultant

The World Bank Group [15/07/2020 - 31/10/2020]

City: Kassel

Country: Germany

Key tasks:

- Setting the field to expand an online educational program nationwide
- $^{\circ}$ Monitoring a team that supports students and teachers while interacting with online solutions
- Solving issues associated with working with new technologies, particularly in remote areas.

Short-term Consultant

The World Bank Group [23/05/2019 - 31/08/2019]

City: Quito

Country: Ecuador

Key tasks:

- Piloting an online intervention designed to train high school students at scale.
- Testing the performance of online education in remote areas
- Training teachers and administrative personnel on the dynamics of working with online solutions at scale.
- Monitoring rapid-fire data collection using phone-based tools. It includes dealing with protocols to mitigate the COVID-19 emergency.

Research Assistant at the Economi Policy, Entrepreneurships and Innovation Unit (EPIE) *University of Kassel* [02/2017 – 04/2018]

City: Kassel

Country: Germany

- Research fields: record linkages, economics of innovation
- Key tasks: literature review, data cleaning, compilation, and preparation.

Senior consultant at the Quantitative Research Center for Economic and Social Development *Quantitative Research Center for Economic and Social Development (Economica-CIC)* [04/2014 – 09/2015]

City: Quito

Country: Ecuador

Research fields: health economics, economics of education, gender economics, environmental economics Key tasks:

- Literature review, data analysis, and drafting of policy notes for decision-makers in Ecuador (i.e., the Ministry of Education, National Secretary of Planning)
- Evaluation of multi-media educative solutions to improve students' situation at scale (qualitative and quantitative assessment).
- Dissemination of research results among policymakers and the general audience.
- Capacity-building in team activities.

Economic Coordinator at Ekos Magazine

Corporación Ekos [03/2010 – 11/2013]

City: Quito

Country: Ecuador

Key tasks:

- Literature review, data analysis, and drafting of journalistic articles about the performance in multiple economic sectors.
- Establishing networks to supply relevant information to our readers.

- Leading teams to audit specialized rankings. The magazine uses the rankings to award the best private companies every year.
- Dissemination of critical information through traditional and non-traditional (digital) media.

PUBLICATIONS

Remote-learning, time-use, and mental health of Ecuadorian high-school students during the COVID-19 quarantine

[2021]

https://doi.org/10.1016/j.worlddev.2020.105225.

Asanov, Igor, Francisco Flores, David McKenzie, Mona Mensmann, and Mathis Schulte. "Remote-learning, time-use, and mental health of Ecuadorian high-school students during the COVID-19 quarantine." *World development* 138 (2021): 105225.

Can a role model intervention mitigate the harmful effects of poverty on aspirations? Lessons from Ecuador

[2022]

Francisco Flores. "Can a role model intervention mitigate the harmful effects of poverty on aspirations? Lessons from Ecuador". Working Paper.

Effects of a Role Models Intervention on Promoting STEM and Entrepreneurship Activities among High School Students

[2022]

Asanov, Igor, Atstebro, Thomas; Buenstorf, Guido; Creponm Brunó, Francisco Flores, David McKenzie, Mona Mensmann, and Mathis Schulte. "Effects of a Role Models Intervention on Promoting STEM and Entrepreneurship Activities among High School Students" Working Paper.

System-, Teacher-, and Student-level Interventions for Improving Participation in Online Learning at Scale in High Schools

[2022]

Asanov, Igor, Asanov (Noha), Anastasyia, Atstebro, Thomas; Buenstorf, Guido; Creponm Brunó, Francisco Flores, David McKenzie, Mona Mensmann, and Mathis Schulte. "System-, Teacher-, and Student-level Interventions for Improving Participation in Online Learning at Scale in High Schools." Working Paper.

Empresas y microempresas: identificación de necesidades y demanda de productos, servicios y perfiles laborales deseados en las ciudades de Quito, Guayaquil, y Cuenca

[2015]

Económimca-CIC (2015). Policy brief for the Alto Comisionado para las Naciones Unidas para los Refugiados (ACNUR)

HONOURS AND AWARDS

Grant secured: SIEF's COVID-19 Emergency Window

The World Bank Group [06/2020]

Project: Transitioning from In-School to At-Home Virtual Learning in High Schools: Lessons from Ecuador during the Covid-19 shutdown

https://www.worldbank.org/en/programs/sief-trust-fund/brief/covid-19-emergency-window

Path to Scale Award

Innovation for Poverty Action (IPA) [11/2019]

Project: Showing Life Opportunities: Increasing opportunity-driven entrepreneurship and STEM careers through online courses in schools

https://www.poverty-action.org/program-area/small-and-medium-enterprises/path-to-scale-research

Grant secured: SIEF Nimble evaluations

The World Bank Group [10/2018]

Project: Showing Life Opportunities: Increasing opportunity-driven entrepreneurship and STEM careers through online courses in schools

https://www.worldbank.org/en/programs/sief-trust-fund/brief/nimble-summaries

Grant secured: IGL Grants Program

Innovation Growth Lab (IGL) [03/2018]

Project: Showing Life Opportunities: Increasing opportunity-driven entrepreneurship and STEM careers through online courses in schools

https://www.innovationgrowthlab.org/blog/showing-life-opportunities-increasing-opportunity-driven-entrepreneurship-and-stem-careers

NETWORKS AND MEMBERSHIPS

Innovation for Poverty Action

[Global, 05/2020 - Current]

https://www.poverty-action.org/people/francisco-flores

International Center for Higher Education Research (INCHER)

[Kassel, Germany, 05/2019 - Current]

https://www.uni-kassel.de/forschung/en/27/incher/people/flores-francisco

Economics Science Association

[Global, 05/2018 - Current]

CONFERENCES AND SEMINARS

Aspirations, Poverty and Education: Can a role model intervention mitigate the consequences of deprivation? Lessons from Ecuador

[University of Bologna, 31/08/2022 – 03/09/2022]

Flores, F.: Aspirations, Poverty and Education: Can a role model intervention mitigate the consequences of deprivation? Lessons from Ecuador. ESA European Meeting. September 3rd, Bologna (Italy).

https://www.esabologna2022.com/

Effects of a Role Models Intervention on Promoting STEM and Entrepreneurship Activities among High School Students

[Universidad San Francisco de Quito (USFQ), 04/07/2022 – 07/07/2022]

Flores, F.: Effects of a Role Models Intervention on Promoting STEM and Entrepreneurship Activities among High

School Students. Experimental Economics Conference 2022 (USFQ). July 7th, Galapagos (Ecuador). (Co-authors: Asanov I., Astebro T., Bünstorf G., Crépon B., McKenzie D., Mensmann M., Schulte M.)

https://www.usfq.edu.ec/en/node/3417

Effects of a Role Models Intervention on Promoting STEM and Entrepreneurship Activities among High School Students

[Massachusetts Institute of Technology - Sloan School of Management (MIT), 13/06/2022 – 16/06/2022]

Flores, F.: Effects of a Role Models Intervention on Promoting STEM and Entrepreneurship Activities among High

School Students. ESA World Meeting. June 15th, Boston (USA). (Co-authors: Asanov I., Astebro T., Bünstorf G., Crépon B., McKenzie D., Mensmann M., Schulte M.)

https://sites.google.com/wellesley.edu/esaboston2022/welcome

Effects of a Role Models Intervention on Promoting STEM and Entrepreneurship Activities among High School Students

[University of Chicago, 08/06/2022 - 09/06/2022]

Flores, F.: Effects of a Role Models Intervention on Promoting STEM and Entrepreneurship Activities among High

School Students. Advance in Field Experiments Meeting (AFE). June 9th, Chicago (USA). (Co-authors: Asanov I., Astebro T., Bünstorf G., Crépon B., McKenzie D., Mensmann M., Schulte M.)

https://economics.uchicago.edu/content/afe2022

Effects of a Role Models Intervention on Promoting STEM and Entrepreneurship Activities among High School Students

[University of Copenhagen, 29/03/2022 - 29/03/2022]

Flores, F.: Effects of a Role Models Intervention on Promoting STEM and Entrepreneurship Activities among High

School Students. Copenhagen Education Network Workshop (CEN). March 29th, Copenhagen (Denmark). (Coauthors: Asanov I., Astebro T., Bünstorf G., Crépon B., McKenzie D., Mensmann M., Schulte M.)

https://www.cbs.dk/en/research/departments-and-centres/department-of-economics/research/copenhagen-education-network-cen

Impacts of Personal Initiative and Negotiations Training on Remote-Learning, Time-Use, and Mental Health of Ecuadorian High-School Students during the COVID-19 Quarantine

[Virtual, 10/09/2020 - 12/09/2020]

Flores, F.: Impacts of Personal Initiative and Negotiations Training on Remote-Learning, Time-Use, and Mental Health of Ecuadorian High-School Students during the COVID-19 Quarantine. ESA World Meeting. September 11th, Virtual. (Co-authors: Asanov I., McKenzie D., Mensmann M., Schulte M.)

https://www.economicscience.org/page/conference/2020-esa-global-online-around-the-clock-meetings

Showing Life Opportunities: Increasing opportunity-driven entrepreneurship and STEM careers through online courses in schools

[Humboldt-University Berlin, 28/06/2018 - 01/07/2018]

Flores, F.:Showing Life Opportunities: Increasing opportunity-driven entrepreneurship and STEM careers through online courses in schools. ESA World Meeting. july 1st, Berlin (Germany). (Co-authors: Asanov I., Astebro T., Bünstorf G., Crépon B., McKenzie D., Mensmann M., Schulte M.)

https://www.economicscience.org/page/conference/2018-esa-world-meeting-berlin-germany

LANGUAGE SKILLS

Mother tongue(s): Spanish

Other language(s):

English German

LISTENING C2 READING C2 WRITING C2 LISTENING A2 READING A2 WRITING A2

SPOKEN PRODUCTION C2 SPOKEN INTERACTION C2 SPOKEN PRODUCTION A2 SPOKEN INTERACTION A2

DIGITAL SKILLS

My Digital Skills

Programming and Typesetting (Matlab, Python, STATA, R, SQL, Aimms, LATEX) / Microsoft Office / Social Media